Finding Aid for Betty Frankel papers, 1958-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Betty Frankel papers 1958-1993
Frankel, Betty.
5.25 linear feet
2012086 Aa 2
Betty Frankel was an award-winning writer for the Observer and Detroit Free Press newspapers. The Betty Frankel Papers document her career as a writer for over three decades. The majority of the collection is comprised of Frankel's weekly columns in the Observer and Detroit Free Press.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Richard W. Frankel (donor no. 10705 ) in January 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Betty Frankel was an award-winning writer for the Observer and Detroit Free Press newspapers, where she authored the garden and landscape columns for more than three decades. She graduated from the University of Michigan with a Bachelor of Science degree in botany and a Master's degree in landscape architecture in 1973. She and her husband, Richard, resided in the northern suburb of Farmington Hills. Frankel belonged to many professional organizations, including the Garden Writers Association of America Inc., the Landscape Critics Council of the Federated Garden Clubs of Michigan Inc. (of which she was a charter member), and the Cranbrook Gardens Auxiliary. Her in-depth articles of landscaping and gardening earned Frankel numerous awards, with official recognition coming from the Garden Writers Association of America Inc., the Women's National Farm and Garden Association Inc., and the Metropolitan Detroit Landscape Association. On February 21, 1993, Frankel passed away at the age of 69.
The Betty Frankel Papers document her career as a writer for over three decades. The majority of the collection is comprised of Frankel's weekly columns in the Observer and Detroit Free Press. Materials are arranged into two series: Personal and Publications. Taken together, the Betty Frankel Papers chronicle the growth and development of gardening and landscapes techniques across the Metropolitan Detroit area from the 1960's through the 1990's.
Subjects:
Frankel, Betty.; Gardening--Michigan--Detroit.; Horticulture--Michigan--Detroit.; Women in landscape architecture--Michigan.; Women journalists--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit free press.; Observer & eccentric.
- Personal
  The Personal series contains awards, notebooks, calendar books, and a sketch diary. The awards include original certificates from the award ceremonies in addition to press coverage of the events as well as correspondence informing Frankel of her selection. The notebooks primarily consist of information Frankel used for stories that would later be published. They span from 1977 to 1989 with no significant gaps. The calendar books are appointments and meetings Frankel scheduled in order to complete her stories. The sketches can be found in one notebook with no dates. In the book are illustrations of nature sites that reflect Frankel's interest in landscaping.
  - Awards, 1971-1979 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Notebooks
    - 1977-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1989 (Box 1)
  - Memo & Date Books, 1978-1983 (Box 1)
  - Sketch Diary, undated (Box 1)
- Publications
  The Publications series is first organized by format (newspapers, books, and miscellaneous) then by company. The newspaper clippings derive from the Detroit Free Press, the Observer, and the Farmington Enterprise & Observer. They are arranged chronologically by year and an index for the year's article can be found at the beginning of most folders. Both books in the series were published by the Free Press. The publication of Adventures in Landscaping in 1973 also fulfilled the requirements for Frankel's master's degree in landscape architecture at the University of Michigan.
  - Newspapers
    - Compiled Clippings, 1958-1971, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Detroit Free Press
      - Clippings
        - 1969-1973, 6 folders (Box 1)
        - 1974-1979, 12 folders (Box 2)
        - 1980-1984, 10 folders (Box 3)
        - 1985-1988, 9 folders (Box 4)
        - 1989-1993, 9 folders (Box 5)
      - Promotional Articles, 1971-1976 (Box 5)
      - Gardening Guides, 1974-1985 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Detroit World Clippings, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Farmington Enterprise & Observer Clippings, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    - Observer Clippings, 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Books
    - Adventures in Landscaping, 1973 (Box 6)
    - 1986 Garden Calendar, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - "A Presentation for Lawn & Garden Advertisers," 1987 (Box 6)
    - "Earthly Delights," 1990 (Box 6)
    - "Sail into Columbus and Discover AmeriFlora '92," 1992 (Box 6)